Guide to the Jacques Lacomblez Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Jacques Lacomblez papers
1952-2016
GEN MSS 1437
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.75
(5 boxes)
The Jacques Lacomblez Papers contains correspondence, writings, printed material, photographs, electronic media, and other papers by or relating to Jacques Lacomblez, his art and publishing practices, and his relationships with other artists.
Lacomblez, Jacques
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 5 (electronic media): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Philippe Luiggi on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2017.
Arrangement
Organized into five series: I. Writings, 1960-2016. II. Correspondence, 1958-2015. III. Photographs and artwork, 1952-2011. IV. Exhibition Catalogs, Announcements, and Invitations, 1952-2015. V. Electronic Media, 2011.
Jacques Lacomblez
Jacques Lacomblez, a Surrealist painter and poet, was born in Brussels, Beligium in 1934. Lacomblez began exhibiting his paintings in 1952, published his poetry extensively, and collaborated with other Surrealist artists and authors. Additionally, Lacomblez created "Edda," an avant-garde art and poetry magazine, producing five issues between 1958-1965.
Scope and Contents
The Jacques Lacomblez Papers, which span from 1952 to 2016, contain correspondence, writings, printed material, photographs, electronic media, and other papers by or relating to Jacques Lacomblez. Materials document Lacomblez's artistic practice, his involvement with publishing including the production of "Edda" magazine, and his relationships with other artists and creatives.
Art, Belgian -- 20th Century; Art, Belgian -- 21st century; Belgian poetry (French) -- 20th Century; Belgian poetry (French) -- 21st century; Poets, Belgian -- 20th Century -- Archives; Surrealism -- 20th Century; Surrealism -- 21st century; Born digital; Poets -- Belgium -- 20th Century; Poets -- Belgium -- 21st century; Painters -- Belgium -- 20th Century; Painters -- Belgium -- 21st century; Lacomblez, Jacques
- Writings, 1960-2016; Series I; 0.42; (1 box)
  Arrangement
  Material within this series maintains the original organization found at time of acquisition, which is roughly chronological.
  - Artist tracts and statements, 1960-2003 (Box 1)
  - Tir de Barrage, 1960 (Box 1)
  - Identite-Achilee Chavee; Ombres Libres, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Filigranes, 1963-1974 (Box 1)
  - Grande Ligne, 1968-1974 (Box 1)
  - Poeme de, et pour (Ain si dire); Stain Jean de la Croix, 1974 (Box 1)
  - L'agonie l'heure levent meles, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Le Ballon Sur Le Fleuve, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Le Sang Circule, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Eurydice: Ou La Topographie Impossible, 1977 (Box 1)
  - Art et Alchimie Pour a Schwarz, 1986 (Box 1)
  - Pour une phrase voilee, 1986-1994 (Box 1)
  - Le Voyageur Immobile, 1994-1997 (Box 1)
  - Blason Funebre pour Villiers de L'isle Adam, 1996 (Box 1)
  - Elegie, 1996 (Box 1)
  - Le Jardin de Mallarme (Tombeau), 1996 (Box 1)
  - "Bois Flottes" and notebooks, 2008-2013 (Box 1)
  - Jetees D'Exil, 2009-2013 (Box 1)
  - Presque Rien, 2011 (Box 1)
  - De Derive et D'instant, 2012-2015 (Box 1)
  - Texte D'Hommage a Jean-Claude Charbonel Decede, 2016 (Box 1)
  - Project inedit de publication de letteres de Henri de Salignac, Louis de Baviere, Don Felipe, undated (Box 1)
  - A Propos de la Creativite de Lucques Trigant, undated (Box 1)
- Correspondence, 1958-2015; Series II; 0.83; (2 boxes)
  - Correspondence related to Edda magazine, 1958-1967 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence related to Edda magazine, 1958-1967 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence from Jean Thiercelin, 1959-1968 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence related to Revue Edda, 1963-1964 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence from Claude Tarnaud, 1963-1987; 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Correspondence from Claude Tarnaud, 1963-1987; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Correspondence from Jacques Lacomblez to Andre Breton, Edouard Jaguer, and others, 1963-2015 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence from Claude Tarnaud, Edouard Jaguer, and Jean Thiercelin, 1966 (Box 3)
- Photographs and artwork, 1952-2011; Series III; 0.42; (1 box)
  - Photographs of Jacques Lacomblez and others, 1966 (Box 3)
  - Collection of original watercolors by Jacques Zimmermann, 1993 (Box 3)
- Exhibition catalogs, announcements, and invitations, 1952-2016; Series IV; 0.67; (2 boxes)
  Material within this series are arranged in chronological order.
  - Unsorted exhibition catalogs, announcements, and invitations, 1952-2016 (Box 3)
  - Jacques Lacomblez exhibition catalogs, 1953-2015 (Box 3)
  - Jacques Lacomblez exhibition catalogs, 1953-2015 (Box 4)
  - Exhibition invitation to Pierre Demarne and Henri Pinhas show, 1958 (Box 4)
  - "Phases" artist exhibition catalogs and invitations, 1958-1999 (Box 4)
  - "Phases" artist exhibition catalogs and invitations, 1958-1999 (Box 4)
  - "Phases" artist exhibition catalogs and invitations, 1958-2004 (Box 4)
  - Benjamin Peret: 3 Poemes Inedits, 2006 (Box 4)
- Electronic Media, 2011; Series V; 0.25; (1 box)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - Jacques Lacomblez, Marxiste et Surrealiste; Les Voyageurs du Temps des Revues Armorigenes, 2011 (Box 5)